Finding Aid for Charles W. Joiner papers, 1945-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles W. Joiner papers
1945-1985
Joiner, Charles Wycliffe, 1916-
851585 Aa 2
Professor of law at University of Michigan, chairman of the University's sesquicentennial celebration, Dean of the Wayne State University Law School, U.S. District Judge. papers include correspondence and other papers concerning his academic career, legal interests, and the administration and preparation for the sesquicentennial celebration; also correspondence and reports relating to his service on such judicial committees as the Advisory Committee on Rules of Evidence, National Conference Committee on Uniform State Laws, the Ethics Committee of the American Bar Association; and materials concerning his work with the Michigan Blue Cross-Blue Shield insurance program
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
58 linear feet
Donor number 4581.
The collection is open to research.
Charles W. Joiner served as professor of law at the University of Michigan, 1947-1968, dean of the Wayne State Law School, 1968-1972, and U.S. district judge, 1972-1988.
Joiner was born 1916 in Maquoketa, IA. He received his B.A. and J.D. degrees from the University of Iowa in 1937 and 1939 respectively/ After wartime service and five years of private practice he joined the University of Michigan faculty as assistant professor in 1947. He was promoted to associate professor in 1950 and professor in 19553. He served as associate dean of the Law school in 1960-1965 and as acting dean in 1964-1965. In 1967, Joiner chaired the university's sesquicentennial celebration.
As teacher and scholar Joiner devoted himself primarily to civil procedure and trial practice. He authored or co-authored six books on these subjects. He pioneered one of the first simulated litigation courses in the country, using films of accidents form various angles to prepare witnesses for testifying in moot court exercises. He also helped organize the annual Advocacy Institute.
Joiner left the Law School in 1968 to become dean of the Wayne State University Law School. He was nominated by Richard M. Nixon on April 25, 1972, to a position on the U. S. District Court, Eastern District of Michigan, to a seat vacated by Talbot Smith; He was confirmed by the Senate on June 8, 1972, and received commission on June 9, 1972. joiner assumed senior judge status on August 15, 1984.
Joiner was a major figure in the legal profession at both the regional and national levels. He was co-director of the research and drafting committee of the Michigan Constitutional Convention of 1961-1962 and president of the State Bar in 1970-1971. Beginning in 1973 he served as commissioner on Uniform State Laws. In 1977-1978 he served as chairman of the American Bar Foundation. He also chaired the American Bar Association's committee on specialization in 1952-1956 and its section on individual rights and responsibilities in 1976-1977. For many years Joiner had a principal hand in drafting rules of evidence and procedure for the federal and state courts.
The Charles W. Joiner papers include correspondence and other papers concerning his academic career, legal interests, and the administration and preparation for the University of Michigan Sesquicentennial celebration; also correspondence and reports relating to his service on such judicial committees as the Advisory Committee on Rules of Evidence, National Conference Committee on Uniform State Laws, the Ethics Committee of the American Bar Association; and materials concerning his work with the Michigan Blue Cross-Blue Shield insurance program. The papers are organized into two series: Correspondence, 1947-1964, and Subject files. The correspondence is arranged chronologically. Subject files include material relating to his teaching and research, professional activities, and the University Sesquicentennial Committee.
Subjects:
Advisory Committee on Rules of Evidence.; American Bar Association.; Blue Cross and Blue Shield of Michigan.; Insurance--United States.; Law.; Lawyers--Michigan.; State Bar of Michigan.; National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.Law School.; University of Michigan. Sesquicentennial Office.
- Correspondence
  - 1947-1953 (Box 1)
  - 1948 (Box 1)
  - 1948 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1958 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1953 (Box 1)
  - 1953-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1953-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1954 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958 (Box 1)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1959 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
- Subject Files
  - Court cases, papers concerning (Box 2)
    - 1945 (Box 2)
    - 1946 (Box 2)
    - 1946-1950 (Box 2)
    - Concerning practice court, 1947-1952 (Box 2)
    - 1948 (Box 2)
  - Concerning economic survey, 1948-1951 (Box 2)
  - Concerning evidence, 1948-1954 (Box 2)
  - Concerning the Junior Bar Association, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - Concerning the American Association of Law Schools, 1949-1951 (Box 2)
  - Concerning court cases, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Concerning the American Bar Association, 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Concerning the Committee on Civil Procedure, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Concerning pre-trial procedure, 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Concerning trial and appellate practice, 1951 (Box 2)
  - 1951, undated (Box 2)
  - Concerning the American Association of Law Schools, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Concerning the Committee on Civil Procedure, 1952 (Box 2)
  - 1947 (Box 3)
  - 1948 (Box 3)
  - 1949 (Box 3)
  - Concerning the American Law Student Association, 1950 (Box 3)
  - Concerning trials and appeals, 1951 (Box 3)
  - 1954-1958 (Box 3)
  - Include brochures, 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - Concerning a conference on the revision of the Michigan constitution, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Concerning legal education, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
  - Concerning the American Bar Association, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Concerning the American Law Institute, 1953-1954 (Box 4)
  - Concerning the Committee on Civil Procedure, 1953; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Concerning court cases, 1953-1954 (Box 4)
  - Concerning the American Association of Law Schools, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Concerning the American Bar Association, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Concerning training in law, 1954-1955 (Box 4)
  - Concerning judicial administration, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Concerning judicial selection, 1954-1955 (Box 4)
  - Concerning the State Bar of Michigan, 1954-1958 (Box 4)
  - Concerning the University of Michigan Senate, 1954-1957 (Box 4)
  - Concerning Judicial conference, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Concerning the Michigan Law Institute, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Concerning the Committee on Civil Procedure, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Concerning rules of evidence, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Concerning the summer session at the University of Michigan, 1960-1961; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Concerning George Romney's voting record, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Concerning the Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1963; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Concerning the Council on State Governments, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Concerning constitutional implementation, 1963; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Concerning reorganization of the justice of the peace system, 1963 (Box 5)
  - 1964 (Box 5)
  - Concerning report of the Governor's Special Commission on Traffic Safety, 1964 (Box 5)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - Undated, concerning trial practice (Box 5)
  - Concerning Committee on Civil Procedure, 1956-1957 (Box 6)
  - Concerning Civil Procedure III (course), 1956 (Box 6)
  - Concerning Introduction to Law (course), 1956 (Box 6)
  - Concerning Judicial Administration (course), 1956 (Box 6)
  - Concerning State Bar of Michigan, 1956; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Concerning civil procedure, 1957 (Box 6)
  - Concerning jurisdiction and judgments, 1957-1958 (Box 6)
  - Concerning University of Michigan Senate, 1957-1958 (Box 6)
  - Concerning Case Club, 1958 (Box 6)
  - Concerning Curriculum Committee, 1958 (Box 6)
  - Concerning Judicial Conference, 1958 (Box 6)
  - Concerning Pleading and Joiner, 1958-1959 (Box 6)
  - Concerning the Public Service Commission, 1958 (Box 6)
  - Concerning the American Law Institute, 1956-1957 (Box 7)
  - Concerning Joint Committee on Michigan, 1956-1957 (Box 7)
  - Concerning Michigan Procedural Revision, 1956-1959; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Concerning Michigan Procedural Revision Meeting, 1956; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Concerning the American Law Student Association, 1957-1958 (Box 7)
  - Concerning civil procedure, 1957 (Box 7)
  - Concerning legal education and admissions to the bar, 1957-1958 (Box 7)
  - Concerning Michigan Procedural Revision Meeting, 1957 (Box 7)
  - Concerning joint committee on Michigan Procedural Revision, 1958-1960 (Box 7)
  - Concerning scholarship committee, 1958-1959 (Box 7)
  - Concerning legal research center, 1959 (Box 7)
  - Concerning sales, 1959 (Box 7)
  - Includes list of publications, 1959 (Box 7)
  - Concerning summer school, 1959-1960; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Concerning summer school, 1960 (Box 7)
  - Concerning Court of Appeals Act, 1957; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Concerning Michigan Procedural Revision, 1960-1961; 10 folders (Box 8)
  - Include term papers, 1959 (Box 9)
  - Undated, concern subversive activity (Box 9)
  - Undated; include brochures (Box 9)
  - Undated; include notes, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Undated; include other law schools (Box 9)
  - Undated; include rough drafts, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - undated, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Concerning the American Law Student Association, 1959 (Box 10)
  - Concerning the practice court, 1959 (Box 10)
  - Concerning Procedural. Revision Meeting, 1959 (Box 10)
  - Concerning State Bar of Michigan, 1959; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Concerning State Bar of Michigan, 1960-1961; 5 folders (Box 10)
  - Concerning Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Concerning Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1961-1962 (Box 10)
  - Concerning constitutional implementation, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Concerning the University of Michigan and Higher education, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Concerning summer school, 1962; 11 folders (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan sesquicentennial celebration (Box 12)
    - 1963, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - 1964, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - 1965, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - 1966, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Concerning Georgetown University's 175th Anniversary, 1966 (Box 12)
    - Concerning Georgetown University's 175th Anniversary, 1966 (Box 12)
    - 1967, 15 folders (Box 13)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 13)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning court case, 1954 (Box 13)
  - Michigan Bar Association
    - Papers (Box 14)
      (not further described)
    - Papers (Box 15)
      (continued)
    - Papers (Box 16)
    - Papers (Box 17)
    - Papers (Box 18)
    - Administration
      - Executive Director (Box 18)
      - Roster (Box 18)
      - Committee Lists, 1970-1971; 2 files (Box 18)
    - Age of Majority (Box 18)
    - Agenda-Monthly Meetings (Box 18)
    - Audit Reports-Assembly Action Assembly Reports, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Bylaws Revision
      - Special Committee to Study Structure of Bar (Box 18)
    - Executive Committee-Elections, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Summary Report-General Counsel (Box 18)
    - Arbitration of Disputes Between Attorneys (Box 18)
    - Bills and Resolutions (Box 19)
    - Board of Law Examiners (Box 19)
    - Character & Fitness Committee (Box 19)
    - Civil Liberties (Box 19)
    - Civil Procedure (Box 19)
    - Commissioner at Large (Box 19)
    - Contingent Fees (Box 19)
    - Corporation, Finance & Business Law (Box 19)
    - Court Administration (Box 19)
    - Computer Program (Box 19)
    - Criminal Code Hearing, 02/10/1971 (Box 19)
    - Criminal Code Revision Committee (Box 19)
    - Criminal Jurisprudence Committee (Box 19)
    - Criminal Justice Program for Michigan (Box 19)
    - Criminal Law Section (Box 19)
    - Crime Prevention Center Committee (Box 19)
    - Drug Information (Box 19)
    - Dues (Box 19)
    - District Court System (Box 19)
    - Economics of Legal Practice
      - Paraprofessionals (Box 19)
    - Election Reform (Box 19)
    - Family Law (Box 19)
    - Firearms Legislation (Box 19)
    - Fiscal Committee (Box 19)
    - General, 1968-1972; 2 files (Box 19)
    - Michigan State Bar Association (Box 20)
    - Grievance Committee-, 1969-1972; 2 files (Box 20)
    - Grievances-Fenton (Box 20)
    - Grievances Rules Revision (Box 20)
    - Grievances Workmen's Compensation (Box 20)
    - Advisory Committee on Rules of Evidence, 1965-1966 (Box 20)
  - Advisory Committee on Civil Rules
    - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 21)
    - File 1/28/66-65 (Box 21)
    - General Correspondence, 1955-1964 (Box 21)
    - Meeting, 05/20/1966-05/21/1966 (Box 21)
    - Washington, D.C., February 1965 (Box 21)
    - 1965 (Box 21)
    - Letter to Albert Sacks, 11/05/1965 (Box 21)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 21)
    - Books, Pamphlets, Articles, Papers, tee. (Box 21)
  - National Conference Commissioners on Uniform (Box 22)
    - State Laws Meeting, April 1963-December 1963
      - 1964 (Box 22)
      - August 1965 (Box 22)
      - Uniform Installment & Land Sales Act (Box 22)
      - Committee on Uniformity of Judicial Decisions (Box 22)
  - American Law Institute, 12 files (Box 22)
  - American Trial Lawyers Association, 6 files (Box 22)
  - Association American Law Schools, 15 files (Box 23)
  - American Law Student Association, 7 files (Box 23)
  - American Judicature Society, 9 files (Box 23)
  - Amicus in the Matter of Contempt (Box 24)
  - Martin Patrick Brian Lavan (Box 24)
  - Michigan State Bar Civil Action no. 33467 (Box 24)
  - Group Legal Services (Box 24)
  - Housing Law Revision (Box 24)
  - Insurance Law
    - No Fault (Box 24)
  - Institute of Continuing Legal Education (Box 24)
  - Jail Study Committee (Box 24)
  - Judicial Selection & Tenure Committee (Citizens Conference) (Box 24)
  - Judicial Tenure Commission-Judicial Selection & Qualification (Box 24)
  - Judicial Advisory Committee (Box 24)
  - Judicial Conference, 1970 (Box 24)
  - Jury Selection (Box 24)
  - Judicial Article VI Revision 21 member Commission (Box 24)
  - Labor Relations Law (Box 24)
  - Law Day Committee (Box 24)
  - Legal Aid Committee (Box 24)
  - Legal Education (Box 24)
  - Bar Examinations (Box 24)
  - Legislation Committee (Box 24)
  - Legislative Services Bureau (Box 24)
  - Malpractice Insurance (Box 25)
  - Medicolegal Problems (Box 25)
  - Minimum Fee Schedules (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous Committees (Box 25)
  - Michigan Blue Cross-Shield Variable Fee Program (Box 25)
  - Michigan State Bar Foundation (Box 25)
  - Natural Resources Committee (Box 25)
  - OEO-Office of Economic Opportunity (Box 25)
  - Patent Trademark & Copyright Section (Box 25)
  - Personnel Committee (Box 25)
  - Pre-Paid Legal Services (Box 25)
  - Press Relations, (Clippings & Releases) (Box 25)
  - Prison Reform (Box 25)
  - President
    - Appearances (Box 25)
    - President's Page (Box 25)
    - Letters of Congratulations (Box 25)
    - Responsibilities (Box 25)
  - Probate Code Revision Committee (Box 25)
  - Pro Bono Publico Program (Box 25)
  - Professional & Judicial Ethics (Box 25)
  - Public Relations (Box 25)
  - Public Defender (Box 25)
  - Appellate Public Defender Commission (Box 25)
  - Relations Among Lawyers-Accountants-Banks (Box 25)
  - Insurance Companies-Realtors (Box 25)
  - Report from your State Bar Commissioner (Box 25)
  - Resolutions-General (Box 25)
  - Retirement Plans (Box 25)
  - Rules Nos. 11 & 15 (Grievance Rules) (Box 25)
  - (Procedural Rules) (2 files) (Box 25)
  - Discipline & Reinstatement, 12/02/1969 (Box 25)
  - SBM-Sections (Box 26)
  - Sharpe Bill (Box 26)
  - Specialization in Legal Practice No. 1 and 2, 2 files (Box 26)
  - John P. Steketee (Box 26)
  - Supreme Court
    - Code of Professional Responsibilities (Box 26)
    - Judicial Conference, 1970-1971 (Box 26)
    - General (Box 26)
  - Title Standards Committee (Box 26)
  - The Third Judicial Circuit (Box 26)
  - Traffic Courts Committee (Box 26)
  - Unauthorized Practice Committee (Box 26)
  - Upper Peninsula Institute-6111 & 12, 1971 (Box 26)
  - Upper Peninsula Institute-6/26-27, 1970 (Box 26)
  - Young Lawyers Section (Box 26)
  - Workmen's Compensation Section (Box 26)
  - Wayne County Court Structure (Box 26)
  - Meetings:
    - Midyear, 1972 (Box 26)
    - 36th Annual Meeting, 1971 (Box 26)
    - Midyear Meeting, January 22, 1971 (Box 26)
    - Midyear Meeting, 1970 (Box 26)
    - 35th Annual Meeting, 1970 (Box 26)
    - Committee & Chairmen's Breakfast (Box 26)
    - 34th Annual Meeting, 1969 (Box 26)
  - State Bar of Michigan
    - Minutes, 1968-1972 (Box 27)
    - Joint Committee on Continuing Legal Education
      - Foundation for Adult Ed-News Digest (Box 27)
      - ABA & ALI (Box 27)
      - Gen. Correspondence-, 1958-1966 (Box 27)
  - Joint Committee on Continuing Legal Education (Box 28)
    - Second Arden House Conference, 1963 (Box 28)
    - Arden House Conference, 1958 (Box 28)
    - Council on Education of the Bar-Public Responsibility (Box 28)
    - Committee on Royalties (Box 28)
    - Practical Lawyer (Box 28)
    - Future of Continuing Legal Education (Box 28)
    - Minutes (Box 28)
    - Books & Pamphlets (Box 28)
  - ICLE-Shapiro, E. Donald (Box 29)
  - Institute Continuing Legal Ed. (Box 29)
  - General Correspondence, 1960-1966 (Box 29)
  - Reports-Institute Continuing Legal Education (Box 29)
  - Full Time Employees (Box 29)
  - Part-Time Employees (Box 29)
  - Program Correspondence (Box 29)
  - Directorship Applications (Box 29)
  - Young Lawyers Seminar, 1960 (Box 29)
  - Conference of Continuing Legal Education, 1959
    - Organization (Box 29)
  - Executive. Committee. Minutes of Meetings
    - Coordinating Committee (Box 29)
    - Executive Committee, 1960; 1962; 1964; 1966 (Box 29)
  - Negro Student Recruitment (Box 30)
  - Recruitment Admissions Policy Committee (Box 30)
  - Admissions Correspondence (Box 30)
  - Law School space and building, 4 files (Box 30)
  - Curriculum (Box 30)
  - Deanship, 1965-1966 (Box 30)
  - Deanship to other Schools (Box 30)
  - Grade Norms (Box 30)
  - Graduate and Research Committee
    - Ford Foundation (Box 30)
  - Graduate Studies (Box 30)
  - Honorary Degrees (Box 30)
  - Honors Program (Box 30)
  - American Journal of Comparative Law (Box 30)
  - American Journal of Law Reform (Box 30)
  - Law School Judiciary Council (Box 30)
  - Special Committee on Legal Writing (Box 31)
  - Special Library Committee (Box 31)
  - Assignment of Office Space (Box 31)
  - Personnel (Box 31)
  - Placement Correspondence (Box 31)
  - Placement, Fellowships and Scholarships (Box 31)
  - Scholarships (Box 31)
  - Law School Sesquicentennial Conference on Computers (Box 31)
  - Class Reunions (Box 31)
  - Combine Program of Law & Graduate Studies (Box 31)
  - Common Law Burglary Instructions (Box 31)
  - Conference on Comparison of Admin. of Justice (Box 31)
  - Cooley Lectures (Box 31)
  - Corres. Faculty (Ex) (Box 31)
  - Courses and Seminars-Law School (Box 31)
  - Faculty Reports for Report to the President (Box 31)
  - Case Clubs, Faculty Advisor Program (Box 31)
  - Scribes, 8 files (Box 32)
  - National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform. State Laws (Box 32)
    (Includes Michigan Commissioners and Legislative Service)
  - Miscellanea (Box 32)
  - American Bar Association Specialization Files (Box 33)
  - Advisory Committee on Civil Rights (Box 34)
  - Jt. Committee on Court Reorganization (Box 34)
  - University of Michigan Law School (Box 35)
  - University of Michigan Law School (Box 36)
  - American Bar Association Professional Ethics Committee
    - Papers (Box 37)
    - Papers (Box 38)
    - Papers (Box 39)
    - Papers (Box 40)
    - Papers (Box 41)
    - Papers (Box 42)
    - Papers (Box 43)
    - Papers (Box 44)
    - Papers (Box 45)
  - Topical File
    - A-D (Box 46)
    - E-M (Box 47)
    - N-R (Box 48)
    - S-Z (Box 49)
  - Speeches (Box 49)
  - Teaching materials (Box 49)
  - Teaching materials and Judicial Conference of Mich. (Box 50)
  - Judicial Conference of Michigan and Blue Shield of Mich. (Box 51)
  - Blue Shield of Michigan, minutes (Box 52)
  - American Bar Association (Box 53)
  - American Bar Association (Box 54)
  - American Bar Association and American Bar Foundation (Box 55)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 56)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 57)
  - Plymouth Center for Human Development
    (1985 accession)
    - Clippings (Box 58)
    - Correspondence, 1979-1984 (Box 58)
    - Documents, 1978-1983; 2 folders (Box 58)
    - Quarterly Reports, 1979-1985; 21 folders (Box 58)